Coronavirus disease 2019 is an emerging disease with a rapid increase in cases 
and deaths since its first identification in Wuhan, China, in December 2019. 
Limited data are available about coronavirus disease 2019 during pregnancy; 
however, information on illnesses associated with other highly pathogenic 
coronaviruses (ie, severe acute respiratory syndrome and the Middle East 
respiratory syndrome) might provide insights into coronavirus disease 2019's 
effects during pregnancy. Coronaviruses cause illness ranging in severity from 
the common cold to severe respiratory illness and death. Currently the primary 
epidemiologic risk factors for coronavirus disease 2019 include travel from 
mainland China (especially Hubei Province) or close contact with infected 
individuals within 14 days of symptom onset. Data suggest an incubation period 
of ∼5 days (range, 2-14 days). Average age of hospitalized patients has been 
49-56 years, with a third to half with an underlying illness. Children have been 
rarely reported. Men were more frequent among hospitalized cases (54-73%). 
Frequent manifestations include fever, cough, myalgia, headache, and diarrhea. 
Abnormal testing includes abnormalities on chest radiographic imaging, 
lymphopenia, leukopenia, and thrombocytopenia. Initial reports suggest that 
acute respiratory distress syndrome develops in 17-29% of hospitalized patients. 
Overall case fatality rate appears to be ∼1%; however, early data may 
overestimate this rate. In 2 reports describing 18 pregnancies with coronavirus 
disease 2019, all were infected in the third trimester, and clinical findings 
were similar to those in nonpregnant adults. Fetal distress and preterm delivery 
were seen in some cases. All but 2 pregnancies were cesarean deliveries and no 
evidence of in utero transmission was seen. Data on severe acute respiratory 
syndrome and Middle East respiratory syndrome in pregnancy are sparse. For 
severe acute respiratory syndrome, the largest series of 12 pregnancies had a 
case-fatality rate of 25%. Complications included acute respiratory distress 
syndrome in 4, disseminated intravascular coagulopathy in 3, renal failure in 3, 
secondary bacterial pneumonia in 2, and sepsis in 2 patients. Mechanical 
ventilation was 3 times more likely among pregnant compared with nonpregnant 
women. Among 7 first-trimester infections, 4 ended in spontaneous abortion. Four 
of 5 women with severe acute respiratory syndrome after 24 weeks' gestation 
delivered preterm. For Middle East respiratory syndrome, there were 13 case 
reports in pregnant women, of which 2 were asymptomatic, identified as part of a 
contact investigation; 3 patients (23%) died. Two pregnancies ended in fetal 
demise and 2 were born preterm. No evidence of in utero transmission was seen in 
severe acute respiratory syndrome or Middle East respiratory syndrome. Currently 
no coronavirus-specific treatments have been approved by the US Food and Drug 
Administration. Because coronavirus disease 2019 might increase the risk for 
pregnancy complications, management should optimally be in a health care 
facility with close maternal and fetal monitoring. Principles of management of 
coronavirus disease 2019 in pregnancy include early isolation, aggressive 
infection control procedures, oxygen therapy, avoidance of fluid overload, 
consideration of empiric antibiotics (secondary to bacterial infection risk), 
laboratory testing for the virus and coinfection, fetal and uterine contraction 
monitoring, early mechanical ventilation for progressive respiratory failure, 
individualized delivery planning, and a team-based approach with multispecialty 
consultations. Information on coronavirus disease 2019 is increasing rapidly. 
Clinicians should continue to follow the Centers for Disease Control and 
Prevention website to stay up to date with the latest information 
(https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-nCoV/hcp/index.html).