To understand the viral genomic characteristics of a 2019-novel 
coronavirus (2019-nCoV) strain in the first COVID-19 patient found in Hangzhou, 
China. Methods: Viral RNA was extracted in throat swab and sputum sample of the 
patient and was performed real-time reverse transcription PCR detection and 
obtained viral genome by high-throughput sequencing method. Phylogenetic 
analysis was conducted using 29 2019-nCoV genomes and 30 β-coronavirus genomes 
deposited in NCBI GenBank. Fifteen genomes from Wuhan were grouped by mutation 
sites and others were identified by Wuhan's or specific mutation sites. Results: 
A 29 833 bp length genome of the first 2019-nCoV strain in Hangzhou was 
obtained, covering full length of the coding regions of coronavirus. 
Phylogenetic analysis showed that the genome was closest to the genome of a bat 
SARS-like coronavirus strain RaTG13 with an identity of 96.11% (28 666/29 826). 
Among the genes between two genomes, E genes were highly conserved (99.56%), 
while S genes had lowest identity (92.87%). The genome sequence similarities 
among 29 strains from China (Hangzhou, Wuhan, and Shenzhen), Japan, USA, and 
Finland, were all more than 99.9%; however, some single nucleotide polymorphisms 
were identified in some strains. Conclusion: The genome of Hangzhou 2019-nCoV 
strain was very close to the genomes of strains from other cities in China and 
overseas collected at early epidemic phase. The 2019-nCoV genome sequencing 
method used in this paper provides an useful tool for monitoring variation of 
viral genes.
