
Plants have always been a source of drugs for humans since time immemorial. The 
Indian traditional system of medicine is replete with the use of plants for the 
management of diabetic conditions. According to the World Health Organization, 
up to 90% of population in developing countries use plants and its products as 
traditional medicine for primary health care. There are about 800 plants which 
have been reported to show antidiabetic potential. The present review is aimed 
at providing in-depth information about the antidiabetic potential and bioactive 
compounds present in Ficus religiosa, Pterocarpus marsupium, Gymnema sylvestre, 
Allium sativum, Eugenia jambolana, Momordica charantia, and Trigonella 
foenum-graecum. The review provides a starting point for future studies aimed at 
isolation, purification, and characterization of bioactive antidiabetic 
compounds present in these plants.