Fenugreek (Trigonella foenum graecum), a medicinal herb with potent 
antihyperglycaemic and hypoglycaemic effects, is used to treat diabetes. This 
study is aimed to explore the interaction of fenugreek seed extract (FSE) and 
HPT (hypothalamic-pituitary-thyroid) axis in context of leptin secretion which 
have important role in normal and type-1 diabetic subjects. FSE (confirmed to 
contain trigonelline, diosgenin, 4 hydroxyisoleucine) was gavaged (0.25 gm/kg 
body weight/day) to normal and alloxan-induced type-1 diabetic rats for 4 weeks. 
Expression of hypothalamic prepro-TRH (Thyrotropin releasing hormone) mRNA, 
serum levels of TRH, TSH (Thyroid stimulating hormone), fT3, fT4, insulin, 
leptin, glucose; thyroperoxidase activity and growth of thyroid gland, food 
intake, adiposity index were also studied FSE significantly down regulated 
prepro-TRH mRNA expression; decreased serum TRH, TSH, fT3, fT4 levels, and 
regressed thyroid gland in FSE-fed normal and diabetic rats than those observed 
in normal diet-fed control and diabetic rats. FSE decreased (p<0.005-0.001) 
adiposity index and leptin secretion, increased food intake and body weight in 
all FSE-fed rats. FSE improved insulin secretion, decreased glucose level but 
impaired HPT axis in diabetic rats, indicating insulin-independent central 
hypothyroidism. Results suggested that the dominant signal to hypothalamus 
suppressing HPT axis is the fall in leptin level which i resulted from decreased 
adiposity index following FSE feeding. Fenugreek simultaneously having 
hypoglycaemic and hypothyroidal actions raises questions whether it can be 
safely used to treat diabetes and/or hyperthyroidism as was suggested by many 
workers.