Pedicularis longiflora Rudolph (Orobanchaceae) and Allium carolinianum Linn 
(Alliaceae) are two important medicinal plants found in trans-Himalayan 
Changthang. The immunomodulatory potential of these plants has not been 
explored. In the present study, we evaluated the in vitro and in vivo 
immunomodulatory potential of P. longiflora and A. carolinianum in 
alloxan-induced diabetes in Wistar rats. The ethanol extracts of the aerial 
parts of P. longiflora and whole plant parts of A. carolinianum were used for 
studying the in vitro immunomodulatory activity using lymphocyte stimulation and 
cytokine release assays. For the in vivo study, 5 groups of 6 rats per group, 
including alloxan-induced diabetic and plant extract-treated rats, were 
evaluated for cell-mediated immune (CMI) and humoral immune (HMI) responses in a 
42-day experimental trial using doses of 500mg/kg b.wt. for P. longiflora and 
250mg/kgbwt. for A. carolinianum. For P. longiflora, the median effective dose 
was found to be 500mg/kg. The in vitro lymphocyte stimulation index for P. 
longiflora was significantly higher (1.73±0.04, p<0.05) than that for A. 
carolinianum (1.27±0.06). However, the release of transforming growth factor-β1 
(TGF-β1, 15.63±1.00, p<0.05) by P. longiflora was significantly lower than that 
by A. carolinianum (21.61±1.19), suggesting a better immune response by P. 
longiflora than by A. carolinianum. P. longiflora significantly increased the 
ear thickness (53.12%), inflammatory cellular infiltration (200.00±11.42), and 
total leukocyte count (7.44±0.02) compared to A. carolinianum (47.57%, 
165.83±3.96, and 7.01±0.01, respectively). P. longiflora significantly reduced 
the percentage of leukocytes with depolarized mitochondria (3.24±0.16%) and 
apoptosis (1.81±0.07%), and induced a better CMI response than A. carolinianum. 
Significantly (p<0.05) higher hemagglutination titer (28.37±0.80) and IgG 
production (6.43±0.34mg/mL) were observed in the P. longiflora-treated group 
than in the A. carolinianum-treated group (23.93±0.58 and 6.23±0.37mg/mL). 
Plasma tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α) and TGF-β1 levels, and nuclear factor-κB 
(NF-κB) expression were significantly (p<0.05) lower in the P. 
longiflora-treated group than in the A. carolinianum-treated group. This may be 
due to better HMI responses produced by P. longiflora than by A. carolinianum. 
This is the first study to show that P. longiflora ethanol extract has more 
potent in vitro and in vivo immunomodulatory activities than A. carolinianum, 
especially in alloxan-induced diabetic rats. However, further research is needed 
to identify the different molecular mechanisms involved in mediating this 
immunomodulatory response.