ETHNOPHARMACOLOGICAL RELEVANCE: Medicinal plants belong to the oldest known 
health care products that have been used by human beings all over the world and 
are major components of the formulations used in indigenous system of medicine 
practiced in many countries. Besides, finding place as health supplements, 
nutraceuticals, cosmetics, herbal tea etc. there has been a global insurgence of 
interest, including India, leading to enormous research/activities in the area 
of medicinal plants.
AIM OF THE STUDY: The article is aimed to provide the effort and initiatives of 
ICMR towards research on medicinal plants and its contributions on consolidation 
of Indian research on medicinal plants that are very relevant and important in 
the national context.