Nisha Amalaki (NA), formulation with Curcuma longa Linn (Turmeric, Haridra, 
Nisha in Sanskrit; Family: Zingiberaceae) and Phyllanthus emblica Linn (Indian 
gooseberry, Amlaki in Sanskrit; Family: Phyllanthaceae) which is described for 
various diseases including diabetes in ayurvedic texts and Nighantus. The aim of 
the present study was to assess the pharmacokinetic (PK) and pharmacodynamic 
(PD) interactions of chemically standardized NA and Curcuminoids (CE) with 
metformin (MET) in normal and diabetic animals. Oral administration of NA 
(200 mg/kg) and CE (30 mg/kg) was carried out for seven days followed by 
co-administration of MET till fifteen days. MET plasma PK parameters including 
Cmax, AUC0-∞, t1/2, CL and Vd were measured on the eighth day. PD parameters 
including plasma glucose AUC followed by oral glucose tolerance test, 
high-density lipoproteins (HDL), total cholesterol (TC) and triglycerides (TG) 
were measured on the fifteenth day. In normal animals, co-administration of 
NA + MET and CE + MET resulted in significant increase (p < 0.05) in Cmax, 
AUC0-∞, t1/2, and reduction of CL and Vd. We report that co-administration of 
NA + MET and CE + MET significantly (p < 0.01, p < 0.001) reduced plasma glucose 
level, HDL level while a notable reduction in TG and TC level was observed. 
Interestingly, in diabetic condition, co-administration of NA + MET and CE + MET 
indicated a significant decrease (p < 0.05) in Cmax, AUC0-∞, t1/2 and enhanced 
CL and Vd. Hence, to conclude, co-administration of NA + MET and CE + MET 
resulted in beneficial PK and PD interactions leading to antihyperglycemic and 
antihyperlipidemic effects in both conditions. However, PK interaction was 
drastically different in diabetic and normal conditions