
It is critical to integrate medical nutrition therapy (MNT) provided by a 
registered dietician (RD) into primary care of type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM). 
This is necessary to achieve the goals of improving overall metabolic measures 
beyond calorie restriction and weight loss. Misconceptions about nutrition in 
T2DM add to the challenges of executing MNT in a culturally sensitive 
population. The current review provides insights into MNT for the prevention and 
management of T2DM in India, based on both evidence and experience. It revisits 
historical Indian studies and provides information on appropriate dietary intake 
of carbohydrates (60-70%), proteins (~ 20%) and fats (10%) that will be 
acceptable and beneficial in an Indian T2DM population. It discusses nuances of 
types of carbohydrates and fats and explains associations of increased dietary 
fiber intake, balanced intake of low and high glycemic index foods and 
substitution of saturated fats with plant-based polyunsaturated fats in 
improving outcomes of T2DM and attenuating risk factors. The article also 
deliberates upon special patient populations with comorbid conditions and 
diseases and the necessary adjustments needed in their nutritional care. It 
outlines a step-wise approach to MNT involving a careful interplay of nutrition 
assessment, diagnosis, individualization and patient counseling. Overall, the 
success of MNT relies on providing accurate, acceptable and appropriate dietary 
choices for continued patient adherence. Collaborative efforts from 
diabetologists, endocrinologists, internists and RDs are required to prioritize 
and implement MNT in diabetes practice in India.Funding: Signutra Inc.