Curcumin (diferuloylmethane) is the main curcuminoid of the popular Indian spice 
turmeric (Curcuma longa). In the last 50 years, in vitro and in vivo experiments 
supported the main role of polyphenols and curcumin for the prevention and 
treatment of many different inflammatory diseases and tumors.The 
anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, and antitumor properties of curcumin are due to 
different cellular mechanisms: this compound, in fact, produces different 
responses in different cell types. Unfortunately, because of its low solubility 
and oral bioavailability, the biomedical potential of curcumin is not easy to 
exploit; for this reason more attention has been given to nanoparticles and 
liposomes, which are able to improve curcumin's bioavailability. 
Pharmacologically, curcumin does not show any dose-limiting toxicity when it is 
administered at doses of up to 8 g/day for three months. It has been 
demonstrated that curcumin has beneficial effects on several ocular diseases, 
such as chronic anterior uveitis, diabetic retinopathy, glaucoma, age-related 
macular degeneration, and dry eye syndrome. The purpose of this review is to 
report what has so far been elucidated about curcumin properties and its 
potential use in ophthalmology