Both experimental and clinical studies suggest that oxidative stress 
plays a major role in the pathogenesis of both types of diabetes mellitus. This 
oxidative stress leads to β-cell destruction by apoptosis. Hence exploring 
agents modulating oxidative stress is an effective strategy in the treatment of 
both Type I and Type II diabetes. Plants are a major source of anti-oxidants and 
exert protective effects against oxidative stress in biological systems. 
Phyllanthus emblica, Curcuma longa and Tinospora cordifolia are three such 
plants widely used in Ayurveda for their anti-hyperglycemic activity. 
Additionally their anti-oxidant properties have been scientifically validated in 
various experimental in vitro and in vivo models. Hence the present in vitro 
study was planned to assess whether the anti-hyperglycemic effects of the 
hydro-alcoholic extracts of Phyllanthus emblica (Pe) and Curcuma longa (Cl) and 
aqueous extract of Tinospora cordifolia (Tc) are mediated through their 
antioxidant and/or anti-apoptotic property in a streptozotocin induced stress 
model.