 Tinospora cordifolia (Willd.) Miers is known for its therapeutic 
value in Indian traditional medicine for treating diabetes, rheumatoid 
arthritis, jaundice and cardiac diseases. However, information regarding its 
protective role against inflammatory diseases at the molecular level is limited.
PURPOSE: The objective of the present work is to study the antioxidant and 
anti-inflammatory effect of alcoholic and water extracts of T. cordifolia 
(Willd.) Miers leaves in activated human monocytic THP-1 cells.
STUDY DESIGN/METHODS: Phytochemical analyses of the dry leaf extracts of T. 
cordifolia (Willd.) Miers prepared using the solvents alcohol (TCAE) or water 
(TCWE) are performed employing spectrophotometric methods for estimating total 
phenolic and flavonoid content, and the plant material was authenticated by 
detecting T. cordifolia (Willd.) Miers metabolite biomarkers using LC-MS/MS. 
Arachidonic acid (AA)- and lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-activated human monocytic 
(THP-1) cells were used as experimental models to investigate the antioxidant 
and anti-inflammatory activities of the plant extracts. Arachidonic acid 
(AA)-induced reactive oxygen species (ROS) in THP-1 cells were monitored by 
confocal microscopy/spectrofluorimetry and transcript of antioxidant enzyme 
catalase (CAT), by quantitative real time PCR. Lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-induced 
proinflammatory marker like TNF-α at transcription and protein levels in THP-1 
cells were measured by quantitative real-time PCR or ELISA respectively. 
Further, the effect of T. cordifolia (Willd.) Miers extracts on LPS-induced 
NF-κB translocation, and IκB and P-IκB protein levels, were studied by 
immunoblotting and confocal microscopy.