
Withania somnifera, also called 'Indian ginseng', is an important medicinal 
plant of the Indian subcontinent. It is widely used, singly or in combination, 
with other herbs against many ailments in Indian Systems of Medicine since time 
immemorial. Withania somnifera contains a spectrum of diverse phytochemicals 
enabling it to have a broad range of biological implications. In preclinical 
studies, it has shown anti-microbial, anti-inflammatory, anti-tumor, 
anti-stress, neuroprotective, cardioprotective, and anti-diabetic properties. 
Additionally, it has demonstrated the ability to reduce reactive oxygen species, 
modulate mitochondrial function, regulate apoptosis, and reduce inflammation and 
enhance endothelial function. In view of these pharmacologic properties, W. 
somnifera is a potential drug candidate to treat various clinical conditions, 
particularly related to the nervous system. In this review, we summarize the 
pharmacologic characteristics and discuss the mechanisms of action and potential 
therapeutic applications of the plant and its active constituents.