 AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK) is a drug target for treatment 
of metabolic and cardiovascular complications. Extracts of Gentianaceace plants 
exhibit anti-diabetic and anti-atherosclerotic effects, however, whether their 
phyto-constitutents activate AMPK remains to be determined.
METHODS: Molecular docking of Gentiana lutea constituents was performed with 
crystal structure of human α2β1γ1 trimeric AMPK (PDB ID: 4CFE). Binding of 
Amarogentin (AG) to α2 subunit was confirmed through isothermal titration 
calorimetry (ITC) and in vitro kinase assays were performed. L6 myotube, HUH7 
and endothelial cell cultures were employed to validate in silico and in vitro 
observations. Lipid lowering and anti-atherosclerotic effects were confirmed in 
streptozotocin induced diabetic mice via biochemical measurements and through 
heamatoxylin and eosin, Masson's trichrome and Oil Red O staining.
RESULTS: AG interacts with the α2 subunit of AMPK and activates the trimeric 
kinase with an EC50 value of 277 pM. In cell culture experiments, AG induced 
phosphorylation of AMPK as well as its downstream targets, 
acetyl-coA-carboxylase (ACC) and endothelial nitric oxide synthase (eNOS). 
Additionally, it enhanced glucose uptake in myotubes and blocked TNF-α induced 
endothelial inflammation. Oral supplementation of AG significantly attenuated 
diabetes-mediated neointimal thickening, and collagen and lipid deposition in 
the aorta. It also improved circulating levels of lipids and liver function in 
diabetic mice.
CONCLUSION: In conclusion, AG exerts beneficial vasculo-metabolic effects by 
activating AMPK.
GENERAL SIGNIFICANCE: Amarogentin, a naturally occurring secoiridoid glycoside, 
is a promising lead for design and synthesis of novel drugs for treatment and 
management of dyslipidemia and cardiovascular diseases.
