Cooccurrence of Diabetes Mellitus and Alzheimer's disease in elder people 
prompts scientists to develop multitarget agents that combat causes and symptoms 
of both diseases simultaneously. In line with this modern paradigm and as a 
follow-up to our previous studies, the present study is designed to investigate 
the crude methanolic extracts and subsequent CHCl3, n-BuOH, and H2O fractions of 
Acalypha alnifolia, Pavetta indica, and Ochna obtusata for their inhibitory 
activities towards specific targets involved in AD and DM, namely, 
acetylcholinesterase, butyrylcholinesterase, and α-glucosidase (α-Glc). The 
methanolic extract and its derived chloroform fractions exhibited remarkable 
inhibitory capacities with IC50 values being found at the μg/mL level. Further 
studies on most active chloroform fractions presented a prominent ability to 
scavenge DPPH and ABTS reactive species and highest neuroprotective effect 
against H2O2 induced cell injury. Phytochemical analysis showed a large amount 
of phenolics, flavonoids, and terpenoids in active fractions. In conclusion, A. 
alnifolia, P. indica, and O. obtusata could be promising sources for the 
treatment of AD and DM since these fractions induced significant 
anticholinesterase, antidiabetic, antioxidant, and neuroprotection effects 
attributable to phenolic, flavonoid, and terpenoid contents and encourage 
further studies for development of multifunctional therapeutic agent for AD and 
DM dual therapy.
