The human islet amyloid polypeptide (hIAPP) or amylin is the major constituent 
of amyloidogenic aggregates found in pancreatic islets of type 2 diabetic 
patients that have been associated with β-cell dysfunction and/or death 
associated with type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM). Therefore, developing and/or 
identifying inhibitors of hIAPP aggregation pathway and/or compound that can 
mediate disaggregation of preformed aggregates holds promise as a medical 
intervention for T2DM management. In the current study, the anti-amyloidogenic 
potential of Azadirachtin (AZD)-a secondary metabolite isolated from traditional 
medicinal plant Neem (Azadirachta indica)-was investigated by using a 
combination of biophysical and cellular assays. Our results indicate that AZD 
supplementation not only inhibits hIAPP aggregation but also disaggregates 
pre-existing hIAPP fibrils by forming amorphous aggregates that are non-toxic to 
pancreatic β-cells. Furthermore, AZD supplementation in pancreatic β-cells 
(INS-1E) resulted in inhibition of oxidative stress; along with restoration of 
the DNA damage, lipid peroxidation and the associated membrane damage, 
endoplasmic reticulum stress and mitochondrial membrane potential. AZD treatment 
also restored glucose-stimulated insulin secretion from pancreatic islets 
exposed to hIAPP. All-atom molecular dynamics simulation studies on full-length 
hIAPP pentamer with AZD suggested that AZD interacted with four possible binding 
sites in the amyloidogenic region of hIAPP. In summary, our results suggest AZD 
to be a promising candidate for combating T2DM and related amyloidogenic 
disorders