Gymnema sylvestre (Retz.) R.Br. ex Sm. (Asclepiadaceae) is a well-known 
Ayurvedic anti-sweet plant for the treatment of type 2 diabetes mellitus. 
Although it was previously proposed that G. sylvestre exhibits chemical 
variation based on geography, most research on G. sylvestre has used material 
originating from India. Morphological and anatomical descriptions, 
ITS1-5.8S-ITS2 DNA sequencing, and acid hydrolysis analyses showed that 
G. sylvestre samples from Vietnam are distinguishable from those of Indian 
origin and thus suggest a dissimilarity among G. sylvestre samples with 
different geographic distributions. An LC-MS-guided strategy targeting 
3β-glucuronide oleane-triterpenes in the Vietnamese G. sylvestre variety led to 
the isolation of four known compounds and nine previously undescribed compounds, 
named gymnemosides ND1-ND9. None of the isolated compounds were reported in the 
Indian sample, further supporting the geo-diversity of G. sylvestre. Three 
compounds, gymnemosides ND7-9, exerted significant stimulatory effects on the 
uptake of 2-NBDG in 3T3-L1 adipocyte cells and thus have potential as lead 
molecules for anti-diabetes agents.